hi everyone welcome to the second part
of our Solana development walkthrough
series
in this video we'll be going over how to
use the very powerful
spl-token command line interface
in order to do so and get the most out
of it we'll first of all install the
dependencies
set up our Solana local environment then
create
tokens learn how to properly use them
and finally create a digital
non-fungible token
and use them likewise
this tutorial will require you to have a
proper rustup
rustc and cargo installation in your
environment
as well as the Solana command line
interface and
the spl-token package both of which
we'll be going over on more details
throughout this video
as always if more resources are needed
you can count on Solana's official
documentation
as well as the Github repositories which
are well documented
and for more personalized support don't
hesitate to join the Solana official
discord
so fellow developer let's get to work
the token subsection
of the Solana program library already
contains a very detailed walkthrough on
what you need to set up
and run in order to implement both
fungible
and non-vulnerable tokens this is made
incredibly easy
thanks to the Solana core developers
they've already gone through
all the trouble of writing program and
also releasing other bindings
in which you can use both for C and
Cavascript but for this tutorial
we're sticking with rust the first
command we'll need to do
is a simple cargo install spl-token-cli
(command line interface)
this command has a lot of dependencies
so you can brace yourself for some
waiting
but cargo should be able to download and
compile
every single requirement if it doesn't
please check both
your cargo and rust installations or
reach out to us
on discord the spl-token package we just
installed
shares configurations with the Solana
command line interface
we can check that by running Solana
config
get to get an error message please check
your salon
installation or your environment
configuration
if you need to install the command line
interface all you need to do
is run this curl then shell
installation
this message right here should indicate
to us
that the installation went properly to
add the salona binaries
to your environment path you can just
run this other
export command after that we can check
if our command line interface is working
by running Solana --version so
now we can proceed with the token
going back to our token program we'll
check the current
configurations
as you can see by default we're using
the mainnet
to change that we can just change our
configuration
by running Solana config
set --url and
pointing towards the devnet this will
print out the updated configurations
for our next step we'll need the Solana
wallet
there are many methods for you to do
this either
via hardware your wallet or paper wallet
but in our case i'm going to show you
how you can create a file system wallet
associated with the local
.json file so we'll run the following
command
which will output to this directory
the my-keypair.json the command will
prompt us a passphrase
and this password is only applied to our
recovered seed phrase
so I'll choose anything and keep in mind
that right now
we have our key pair json and
all info contained here is totally
unencrypted
so do not share this with anyone
but what you can share with everyone is
your public key and
in order to get that we run the Solana
keygen pub key command
with our file system wallets in hand we
can point the configuration key pair
to the newly created my-keypair.json
by running the config set command once
again with the --keypair flag
and this should do it for the initial
setup simple as that
right now we can use the cargo spl-token
package we just installed
and run the spl-token create token
command
if you get this message it means that we
do not have
enough funds in a wallet in order to
create the
token what's nice here is that our
Solana
common line interface already has an
airdrop feature built into it
so we can just write solana airdrop
the amount of tokens we're requesting
our
public key address which is right here
and then we need to point the url to our
devnet
endpoint and there we go we now have 10
SOL tokens
we can once again run the spl-token
create command
and it should succeed we can check our
supply by running the command as spl-
token supply
and pointing it to our token address
by default it's zero so we now
will need to mint some tokens for that
we'll create a new account associated
with our
main token by running the command
spl-token create account
and give it our address this account
will hold
the minted tokens as usual
this account will have no balance by
default
but let's change that by running as spl-
token mint the address of our original
token and the amount that we want to
mint
so yeah it succeeded if we check
the supply of our newly created token
we can see that we now have a hundred
new tokens created
and likewise if we check the balance
of our recipient address
we'll see that
it's received 100 tokens
now if we want to expand our token into
other accounts
we'll of course need another Solana
wallet
and we can just generate another one by
using
the same command that we used before
then
we can just once again set
our configuration here but point it to
the other key pair that we have
and run the same command to create an
account
with the original token address once
again
we'll need some funds in order to do
that so
there we go now we've created another
account associated with
our initial Solana token another really
cool feature
of the library is that we can use spl-
token
wrap and specify the amount
of SOL tokens that we want to associate
with
our creative token and this basically
allows us to expand
the functionality and usability of the
SOL token
into the spl-token library so we can
treat it
as any other spl-token
would be treated and this really helps
you out
after wrapping our token we can use once
again
the spl-token
account command to check that
we now have another account here that's
running that has almost exactly one
SOL token as a balance and if we want
to change it back
we just need to do the inverse process
we'll need to copy the account address
that we ended up creating
with the wrap command and just use
spl-token
unwrap
there we go if we check our accounts
once again
the former SOL wrapped token is gone
now remember that other account that we
created
let's check it out once again by running
Solana config set
key pair and point it to the other
keypair
that we have as expected it doesn't have
any of our created tokens let's change
that
let's use our minted account here that
we have
and run the new spl-token
transfer command and also the first address
that we pass on is not from the original
token
but from the account associated with the
minting process
so let's use the same command pass on
our original account the amount of
tokens that we need
to transfer and the receiver
address
right now if you once again run Solana
config set
to switch back to the receiver address
we can check that
we now have 42 tokens that we created
and sent it directly to our other user
now remember the second wallet that we
created the receiver had to manually
associate an address in order to receive
our newly created token
and this is a bit of a hassle because in
the real world scenario
people won't actually do that especially
if your token is new
so there is an option called fund
recipient
which the sender him or herself can fund
for
the account creation and also for the
transaction
so in order to do that we generate a new
key
pair for our file system wallet
right now i'm going to airdrop some
tokens into our newly created account
if we skip this part then the Solana
command line interface
is going to tell us that this address
does not exist and
this is not specifically necessary you
just
have to interact with the devnet in
order for it to
commit that the newly created address
exists so we can revert our
configurations
back to our original token minter
and we should be good to go to use the
new
fund recipient option spl-token
transfer fund
recipient and
oh one thing to note we need our
address still so spl
token account
we need the account itself in order to
use this command
so this is going to be it let's not
forget the amount of tokens that we're
transferring
in this case it will be 8 and we can
just
copy the Solana address itself
if we check out
our account here you see that
we did receive the tokens without having
to pay
any fees for that creating an nft
or a digital non-fungible token is
really similar to what we've done so far
but
instead of having the ability to mint
multiple tokens we'll cap the minting
at one so our token is unique
and also has all the other features of
an
ERC-20 like token like transferring
ownership
and so on so first of all let's create a
new account
by running Solana kegen
new and output it to our
nft key pair file
point our configurations towards it
airdrop some SOL tokens
from devnet
and we're good to create another token
let's associate an account to it so we
can mint tokens
and finally mint only a single token
since we're the master account
associated with this token we can
disable the minting by
running spl-token authorize
the address of the token itself and mint
with the flag disabled and that's it
if we check the accounts that we have
you'll see that we have only a single
minted token
and if we check the supply
of our token
you'll see that it stayed stably one
if the owner wants to transfer the nft
he or she can do it using the same
commands that we've been using so far
so let's do it spl
token transfer let's use also
the kind of mandatory in this case
fund recipient options so the
transaction is done
we will need to point our configurations
back to the origin to the receiver
and if we do spl
token account
we'll see that we now have the nft
really simple and intuitive so this is
going to wrap up
another one of our Solana development
walkthrough videos
I really hope you managed to get
everything to work properly
either way congratulations on improving
your blockchain dev skills
if this video helped you out please
leave your like and don't forget to
subscribe to our official youtube
channel
and enable notifications so you don't
miss out on any future uploads
you're more than welcome to join our
community follow Solana on twitter
@solana and join the telegram channel
using the link t.me/solanaio
you can read up on more Solana
related content by following the link
medium.com/solana-labs
and also join the official discord
channel by going through the link
located in the official website
it was a pleasure having you here thank
you so much for watching
and I hope to see you on the next video
bye